Gordon Shrum fonds
Simon Fraser University Archives and Records Management Department
Gordon Shrum fonds
1962 - 1971
F-32
Q106644098
50 cm of textual records 38 photographs
Simon Fraser University Archives and Records Management Department Maggie Benston Student Services Building, Rm. 0400 8888 University Dr. Burnaby British Columbia Canada V5A 1S6 Telephone: 778.782.3805 Email: archives@sfu.ca http://www.sfu.ca/archives
PHYSICAL DESCRIPTION: 8 photographs located in F-32-1-0-10 PHYSICAL DESCRIPTION: 28 photographs located in F-32-1-0-7 PHYSICAL DESCRIPTION: 1 photograph located in F-32-1-0-4
Shrum, Gordon
Gordon Merritt Shrum (1896-1985) was a scientist, teacher, administrator, and the first Chancellor of Simon Fraser University.
He was born in Smithville, Ontario in 1896. He entered the University of Toronto in 1913 with the intention of becoming a teacher. He joined the Canadian Officers' Training Corps in 1915 and joined the army the following year. After serving in France and receiving the Military Medal, he returned to finish his university studies. He received his BA in 1919, MA in 1921 and PhD in 1923 in physics. His notable achievements included liquefying helium in 1923 and discovering the origin of the auroral green line in the Northern Lights in 1925.
Later that year he left Toronto to become professor of physics at the University of British Columbia. Over the next 36 years, he served that institution as an academic and administrator.
During his time at UBC, Shrum became a colonel in the COTC, and received the Order of the British Empire during World War II. He was also appointed a director of the BC Research Council in 1944. In 1958, he served as chairman of a royal commission investigating the BC Power Commission. This led to his appointment as Chair of the BC Energy Board in 1959.
In 1961, Shrum had to leave UBC because he had reached the compulsory retirement age of 65. He was immediately appointed head of BC Electric (later BC Hydro) by Premier W. A. C. Bennett. In that capacity he was responsible for the Peace River hydro project.
Bennett also selected Shrum to create the new university recommended by the Macdonald Report of 1963. Shrum built Simon Fraser University, as it would be named, in 18 months earning it the title of "the Instant University." Shrum served as SFU's first chancellor until June 1969 and continued to head BC Hydro until 1972. In May 1975 he became director of the Vancouver Museum and Planetarium Association and reorganized the museum-planetarium complex at Vanier Park.
Now in his eighties, Shrum was approached by Premier Bill Bennett to take charge of the financially-troubled Robson Square Courthouse project. He successfully completed the project and was next asked to develop a trade and convention centre for Vancouver. He stepped down from this project when the federal government took over construction. Gordon Shrum died at the age of 89 in 1985.
published
Full
Published
Title is based on provenance of the fonds.
The fonds consists of records created, received and collected by Gordon M. Shrum. Records reflect his involvement with Simon Fraser University as Chancellor, his contribution to building the new university and his interest in education and SFU after he retired as Chancellor. Includes correspondence, reports, briefs, memoranda, photographs, architectural drawings, publications, and newspaper clippings.
The fonds was arranged by the Archivist.
Office of the Chancellor; Photographic materials; Textual records; Buildings and structures
All accessions have been processed as of September 2002. No further accruals are expected.
Please consult the inventory for the Gordon M. Shrum collection, F-31, and the inventory for the Office of the Chancellor, F-3.
Series descriptions and file lists are available.
- Subject files, 1962 - 1971; F-32-1; 41 cm of textual records 38 photographs; Physical description: 8 photographs located in F-32-1-0-10 Physical description: 28 photographs located in F-32-1-0-7 Physical description: 1 photograph located in F-32-1-0-4
  published
  Series consists of records relating to a number of issues, activities and areas of interest relating to Gordon M. Shrum's involvement with Simon Fraser University. Records reflect information on the architectural competition to design SFU, convocation, staff, scholarships, and other like topics. Includes correspondence, reports, briefs, memoranda, architectural drawings, and publications.
  - Reference file - University education, 1962 - 1963; F-32-1-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 32-1)
    Textual records
    Open
  - Reference file - University education 1/2, 1963 - 1969; F-32-1-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 32-1)
  - Reference file - University education 2/2, 1963 - 1969; F-32-1-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 32-1)
  - Reference file - other universities, 1962 - 1966; F-32-1-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 32-1)
    Textual records; Photographic materials
  - Simon Fraser, Explorer, 1963 - 1965; F-32-1-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 32-1)
  - Architectural competition, 1963; F-32-1-0-0-6 (Archival box - standard 32-1)
    Photographic materials
  - Architectural competition, 1963; F-32-1-0-0-7; Physical description: 28 photographs (Archival box - standard 32-1)
  - Brief addressed to Vancouver City Council, 30 April 1963, F-32-1-0-0-8 (Archival box - standard 32-1)
  - Construction, 1963 - 1965; F-32-1-0-0-9 (Archival box - standard 32-1)
  - Aerial views, 1964 - 1966; F-32-1-0-0-10; Physical description: 8 photographs (Archival box - standard 32-2)
    Allen, George; Textual records; Photographic materials
  - SFU funding, 1963 - 1969; F-32-1-0-0-11 (Archival box - standard 32-2)
  - SFU building fund campaign, 1964; F-32-1-0-0-12 (Archival box - standard 32-2)
  - Staff appointments (includes President), 1963 - 1964; F-32-1-0-0-13 (Archival box - standard 32-2)
  - Coat of Arms, 1964; F-32-1-0-0-14 (Archival box - standard 32-2)
  - Convocation founders, 1964; F-32-1-0-0-15 (Archival box - standard 32-2)
  - Chancellor, 1962 - 1969; F-32-1-0-0-16 (Archival box - standard 32-2)
  - Board of Governors, 1963 - 1969; F-32-1-0-0-17 (Archival box - standard 32-2)
  - Senate, 1965 - 1967; F-32-1-0-0-18 (Archival box - standard 32-2)
  - Opening Ceremony - September 9, 1965, F-32-1-0-0-19 (Archival box - standard 32-2)
  - Convocation - Installation, October 28, 1965, F-32-1-0-0-20 (Archival box - standard 32-3)
  - Convocation - May 20, 1967, F-32-1-0-0-21 (Archival box - standard 32-3)
  - Convocation, 1968; F-32-1-0-0-22 (Archival box - standard 32-3)
  - Convocation, 1969; F-32-1-0-0-23 (Archival box - standard 32-3)
  - Honorary degrees, 1968 - 1969; F-32-1-0-0-24 (Archival box - standard 32-3)
  - Athletics, 1966 - 1971; F-32-1-0-0-25 (Archival box - standard 32-3)
  - SFU staff, 1966 - 1967; F-32-1-0-0-26 (Archival box - standard 32-3)
  - Canadian Association of University Teachrs (CAUT), 1967 - 1968; F-32-1-0-0-27 (Archival box - standard 32-3)
  - SFU Administration crisis 1/2, 1968 - 1969; F-32-1-0-0-28 (Archival box - standard 32-3)
  - SFU Administration crisis 2/2, 1968 - 1969; F-32-1-0-0-29 (Archival box - standard 32-3)
  - Ministers' Conference on Recreation 1/2, 1966; F-32-1-0-0-30 (Archival box - standard 32-4)
  - Ministers' Conference on Recreation 2/2, 1966; F-32-1-0-0-31 (Archival box - standard 32-4)
- Press clippings, 1963 - 1969; F-32-2; 10 cm of textual records
  Series consists of press clippings collected by and for Gordon M. Shrum. Press clippings reflect information about education and Simon Fraser University.
  - Education, 1969; F-32-2-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 32-4)
  - SFU, 1963 - 1966; F-32-2-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 32-4)
  - SFU, 1964; F-32-2-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 32-4)
  - SFU, 1966; F-32-2-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 32-4)
  - SFU, 1967; F-32-2-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 32-4)
  - SFU, 1968; F-32-2-0-0-6 (Archival box - standard 32-4)
  - SFU, 1969; F-32-2-0-0-7 (Archival box - standard 32-4)